Believe the unbelievable.
The Matrix is a action, science fiction film directed by Lana Wachowski.
Set in the 22nd century, The Matrix tells the story of a computer hacker who joins a group of
underground insurgents fighting the vast and powerful computers who now rule the earth.
Neo, played by Keanu Reeves.
Morpheus, played by Laurence Fishburne.
Trinity, played by Carrie-Anne Moss.
Agent Smith, played by Hugo Weaving.
Oracle, played by Gloria Foster.
Cypher, played by Joe Pantoliano.
The Matrix is a 1999 science fiction action film
written and directed by the Wachowskis.
The first installment in the Matrix film series, it stars Keanu Reeves, Laurence
Fishburne, Carrie-Anne Moss, Hugo Weaving, and Joe Pantoliano.
It depicts a dystopian future in which humanity is unknowingly trapped inside
the Matrix, a simulated reality created by intelligent machines.
The plot follows the computer hacker Neo, who is recruited by
Morpheus into a rebellion against the machines.
Following the success of the Wachowskis' 1996 film Bound, Warner Bros.
gave the directing duo the go-ahead to make The Matrix.
The film's action scenes were influenced by anime and martial arts films, particularly
fight choreography and wire fu techniques from Hong Kong action cinema.
Other influences include Plato's cave, 1990's Telnet hacker
communities, and William Gibson's cyberpunk novel Neuromancer.
The Matrix popularized terms such as the red pill, as well as a novel visual effect known as "bullet time" in which a character's heightened perception is
represented by allowing the action within a shot to progress in slow motion while the camera appears to move through the scene at normal speed.
The Matrix opened in theaters in the United States on March 31, 1999, to widespread acclaim from critics, who
praised its innovative visual effects, action sequences, cinematography and entertainment value.
The film was a box office success, grossing over
$460 million on a $63 million budget.
It became the highest-grossing Warner Bros.
film of 1999 and the fourth-highest-grossing film of that year.
The Matrix received Academy Awards for Best Visual Effects, Best Film
Editing, Best Sound and Best Sound Effects Editing.
It was also the recipient of numerous other accolades, including Best Sound and
Best Special Visual Effects at the 53rd British Academy Film Awards.
The Wachowskis were awarded Best Director and Best Science
Fiction Film at the 26th Saturn Awards.
The Matrix is considered to be among the greatest
science fiction films of all time.
In 2012, it was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress for being "culturally, historically, and aesthetically significant".
The film's success led to two sequels by the Wachowskis, The Matrix
Reloaded and The Matrix Revolutions, both released in 2003.
The Matrix franchise was further expanded through the production of comic
books, video games and an animated anthology film, The Animatrix.
The franchise has also inspired books and theories expanding on some of the
religious and philosophical ideas alluded to in the films.
A fourth film, The Matrix Resurrections, was directed by
Lana Wachowski and was released in 2021.
The film explores themes of man vs machine, martial arts, kung
fu, dreams, artificial intelligence (a.i.).
The tone is thought_provoking.